<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second part of the religious demurrer; by another hand. Or, an answer to a tract called The lawfullnesse of obeying the present government. / By a lover of truth and peace.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth and peace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E530_31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863390</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115589</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115589)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 82:E530[31])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second part of the religious demurrer; by another hand. Or, an answer to a tract called The lawfullnesse of obeying the present government. / By a lover of truth and peace.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth and peace.</author>
                  <author>Ward, Nathaniel, 1578-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Underhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first part was by Nathaniel Ward.</note>
                  <note>"The lawfulnes of obeying the present government" is by Francis Rous.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "against Mr Rous"; "printed by Tho: Underhill June 6 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rous, Francis, 1579-1659. --  Lawfulnes of obeying the present government --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115589:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſecond Part of the Religious DEMURRER; By another Hand. Or, an ANSWER to a Tract called <hi>The Lawfullneſſe of obeying the preſent Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a lover of Truth and Peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the READER;</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the unhappineſſe, of theſe laſt times eſpecially, that men are apt to run, from one extreame to another. As in matter of Religion, we ſee it evident; we are fallen from ſuperſtition, to prophaneſſe: So in the State, from Miſs-Government, to Change of Government; and ſometimes, from one kinde of Tyranny, to another; from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, to Popular; from Tyranny under a lawfull power, to Tyranny under an unlawfull power. And, which is worſt, is not hard to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, inaſmuch as a ſingle Tyrant, is better then many; Regall Tyranny, better then Martiall. And this is the yoke, that at preſent, people moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of; which, it were well, if wiſe men would ſtudy how to remove; not how to fasten it, unavoidably, upon the necks of this Nation. But this is moſt juſt with God (we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledge it,) that ſeeing, we would not bear the eaſie, ſilken yoke of Jeſus Chriſt; he is now putting on us, an iron yoke; which, neither our fathers were, nor we are, nor our posterity will be able to bear. Amongſt thoſe that aſſiſt to the effecting of this (whether ignorantly or intentionally,) this Gent. is one of the firſt, that undertakes, to perſwade this people, to bear this yoke as if we were <hi>populus ad ſervitutem non nati, ſed deſtinati;</hi> and with our own hands, ſhould help to put this yoke, upon our own necks, and rivet it faſt for falling off: which certainly we doe, if once we can be perſwaded, that not only we may voluntarily (becauſe ſinleſly, as we are made beleeve,) but alſo, muſt neceſſarily, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake (not meer coaction) obey an unlawfull power, by the command of God. It is a very ſad thing, and dangerous, for a man to be engaged once, in any ſinfull deſigne, or act; in that, <hi>ſcel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re tuendum eſt ſcelus,</hi> one engagement draws on another: And it is a very great ſnare (we ſee,) for men to be poſſeſt of great eſtates, and places of profit, by that power, which can as eaſily diveſt them of it, if they oppoſe or aſſiſt not their wicked deſignes. If the world be not miſtaken in the Authour of this Tract, they fear him intangled in ſuch a ſnare: otherwiſe (ſay they) he would never undertake the patronage of ſo bad a cauſe; or countenance it, by acting, or aſſiſting the Authours of this change, especially being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to the contrary (as they yet think) by ſo many Oaths and Covenants. What miſchief
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115589:2"/>this Tract may doe (the rather for the worth, and authority of the man,) with perſons fearfull, or loath to ſuffer loſſe, or puniſhment, is not eaſie to ſay: If this Anſwer may give him any light, to ſee his error; his Retractation of it, by writing or his Retreat from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent power, and actors in it, may (if ſpeedily done) help to Antidote, or expell the preſcribed poiſon. Which that it it may be done, is the deſire of a friend of his. The Lord give it a good Iſſue.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Queſtion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether, Thoſe whoſe Title is held unlawfull, yet being poſſeſt of Authority may lawfully be obeyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THere are two great queſtions now in chaſe and agitation, 1. <hi>Whether the preſent power be juſt and lawfull?</hi> 2. <hi>Whether, ſuppoſing them unlawfull, they may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be obeyed?</hi> The firſt of theſe is waved by this Gentleman, as undertaken by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; with what ſtrength or weakneſſe, let others judge. The ſecond is the ſubject of the preſent debate. The Gentleman ſpeaks of a Declaration publiſhed, wherein the grounds of ſetling the preſent Government are expreſt. But for ought I hear, few rationall, conſcientious men are ſatisfied with that Declaration; conſidering thoſe Vowes, Oaths, Covenants, whereby the Authors of it, ſtood before engaged. And whatever the people may do, in ſubmitting to obey this power of the new Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I fear they that altered it, and thoſe that act it on, or they that abet it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be innocent. But let them look to that; We ſhall not, at preſent, diſcuſſe the lawfullneſſe or the unlawfullneſſe of their power, and proceedings, but conſider how far we our felves may ſubmit unto them, without ſin. For this purpoſe we ſhall firſt conſider how the Gent. hath ſtated the queſtion. And we obſerve that he laies it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Lawfullneſſe, not upon the neceſſity of our obedience; For ſo he ſaies, <hi>Though the change of a Government were beleeved unlawfull, yet it may lawfully be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Not it <hi>muſt</hi> neceſſarily, but <hi>may</hi> lawfully be obeyed; and yet his text produced, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, &amp;c. is preſſed with this inference, <hi>Wherefore ye muſt be ſubject, not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake.</hi> Now ſome there are, who are of opinion, that though ſuch an unlawfull power may be obeyed, yet it need not for conſcience ſake be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. if a man will hazard the puniſhment annexed, and ſubmit himſelf to ſuffer it. But it is otherwiſe in a lawfull power in lawfull things; a man is bound to active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto them, and it ſufficeth not, to ſatisfie conſcience, to ſuffer the penalty, but is a reſiſtance of the ordinance of God, which in lawfull commands, requires active obedience, in unlawfull, paſſive. What then is the difference between a lawfull power and an unlawfull, both commanding lawfull things? but this, That a man may, if he will, obey the one, but muſt obey the other; not only paſſively, by ſuffering, if by ignorance, or weakneſſe he neglect the command, but alſo actively, in acting that command, or elſe he ſins. And to this purpoſe the Gent. adds, <hi>page.</hi> 2. <hi>If the powers in that time were ordained of God, and were to be obeyed for conſcience ſake,</hi> &amp;c. where he takes it for granted (as well he may, if the powers were ordained of God) that be the powers never ſo unlawfull; yet they muſt be obeyed for <hi>conſcience ſake.</hi> Yet the queſtion runs only of the lawfullneſſe. That's firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the clearer ſtating of the queſtion, we muſt neceſſarily diſtinguiſh, in many particulars, which the Gent. hath either omitted, or confounded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt diſtinguiſh of a Government: A State may be conſidered, either as <hi>conſtituta,</hi> long ſetled, or <hi>constituenda,</hi> as yet in ſetling: A people may perhaps, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obey a Government, when there is no probability of recovering their loſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115589:2"/>whereas while it is yet in ſetling, they may ſuſpend obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A people alſo may be conſidered, either as <hi>free</hi> to ſettle upon what Government they will, as having no Government yet ſetled, or the line of ſucceſſion being expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: or as <hi>bound</hi> by Oathes and Covenants to a former Government, or Governours, who are oppreſſed in their right, by violent uſurpation. In the firſt, a people may obey an uſurping power; but the queſtion is of the latter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Tyrant alſo who is an uſurping power is of two ſorts; Firſt, by Title, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a Title; Secondly, by oppreſſion; or as the Gent. himſelf expreſſeth it, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>A Tyrant in regard of an unjuſt Title, or in respect of Tyrannicall oppreſſion, when his Title is good.</hi> Now the queſtion is, whether a Tyrant by an unjuſt Title, not only may, but muſt be obeyed, when he commands lawfull things; And whether, as when a lawfull power commands unlawfull things, he may juſtly, yea muſt be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed; ſo, when an unlawfull power commands lawfull things, he muſt be obeyed?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Obedience is differenced, into active and paſſive. The latter may be yeelded, when the former may not, at leaſt needs not: As when a lawfull power commands unlawfull things, a man muſt ſuffer, not doe: ſo when an unlawfull power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands lawfull things, a man perhaps may obey, but not neceſſarily muſt; at leaſt this is the queſtion now in hand.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe we have occaſion to look at impoſſibility, in this diſcourſe, we muſt difference it alſo here, it is either Preſent, as when there is at preſent an over-ruling power which we cannot withſtand: or elſe Abſolute, when there is a totall ceſſation of all hopes of recovery of the former Government; the heirs, and lawfull ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, being either all naturally dead, or unnaturally extinct, and ſlain; as it was ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be, in <hi>Athalia's</hi> caſe: the people thought ſhe had ſlain all the Royall ſeed, and perhaps upon that ground, knowing of none ſurviving, they ſubmitted to her Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; but as ſoon as they knew <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> one of that Line, was alive, they ſhook off their obedience to her. Theſe things being thus premiſed, we conſider the ſtrength of his Arguments.</p>
            <p>The firſt baſis of all his building, is taken from the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, &amp;c. <hi>The Apostle</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>treating of purpoſe, upon the duty of obedience to Authority, laies down this precept; Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> &amp;c. and hereupon infers; <hi>wherefore you muſt needs be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ject, not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this; Let it firſt be obſerved, that he concludes more then he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to prove: His queſtion was of the lawfullneſſe, but his proof is for the neceſſity of obedience, active, as well as paſſive; Now I would gladly know, what difference there is, in our obedience, to lawfull powers, and to unlawfull powers,<note place="margin">The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> lawfull authority not uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power. Script. &amp; Reaſ. pag. 5, 6. Pag. 4.</note> if it be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to both.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The queſtion is, in this Text, of what power the Apoſtle ſpeaks; of Lawfull, or Tyrannicall; and if of Tyranicall, whether of a Tyrant by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Title, or a Tyrant in regard of oppreſſion; and the judgement of very able Divines is, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of a legall power; not of a Tyrannicall, in either ſenſe: This latter, is learnedly and largely diſcuſſed by the Authour of that Tract; called, <hi>Scripture and Reaſon for Defenſive Arms:</hi> who aſſerts, and proves, the text is not meant of any powers whatever, but of Legall powers, not Tyrannicall at all. His Arguments are theſe from the context: 1. If I be bound to be ſubject to Tyranny by vertue of the commandment here; then Tyranny is the Ordinance of God (for the Apoſtle argues
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115589:3"/>for ſubjection, from Gods ordaining the power) But this is falſe: Therefore ſo is that, that I ſhould be ſubject to Tyranny. 2. He brings many Arguments againſt this Gentlemans Interpretation.<note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> 1. The Magiſtrate that muſt be obeyed is the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God. 2. Not a terrour to good works, but to evil. 3. The Miniſter of God to thee for good. But a Tyrant is not the Ordinance of God; is a terrour to good works: is not the Miniſter of God for good; Therefore not to be obeyed. I confeſſe he carries it all along, of a Tyrant by oppreſſion, whoſe Title is lawfull and juſt; and he ſpeaks (more then we argue for) of Reſiſtance of ſuch a Tyrant; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we plead only for non-obedience; or againſt neceſſity of obedience, to a Tyrant, in regard of unlawfull Title. We ſay then the Gent. miſinterprets, and ſo miſapplies the text, which ſpeaks only of a lawfull power, not of an unlawfull.</p>
            <p>But he goes on, to prove his aſſertion, that the Apoſtle meant it of a power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully gotten; by applying it to the then preſent Roman powers: It was either <hi>Claudius,</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> that then ruled: who were both made Emperours by the Souldiery, againſt the Wills, and Reſolutions of the Conſuls, and Senate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt, he takes it for granted (which cannot well be proved) that becauſe the Apoſtle writ in their times, therefore he meant it of thoſe powers, that they were ordained of God: not by his permiſſion only, but approbation alſo. Whereas the Apoſtle might mean it (and we have heard, did ſo mean it) of any legall power; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractedly, from the <hi>Roman,</hi> or any particular State. 2. But grant it meant of them, yet it is known, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had gotten the conſent of the Senate, and people: and they ſucceeded upon the ſame Title, and ſo might be lawfull powers. 3. This Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is of no force in our caſe; for though it hold parallell, in the Inſtruments of ſetling, or rather changing of the Government, the Souldiery; yet not in the Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it by Senate, and people. Mark the words of the Hiſtorian, engliſhed by the Gent. <hi>pag.</hi> 3. <hi>This ſentence of the Souldiers, was followed with the conſent of the Senate; and then it was not ſcrupled in the provinces: That is, it was conſented to by the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the people.</hi> But ours hath neither conſent of Senate (in its true and full Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) nor people, but the Renitency, yea Abhorrency of both, for the far greater part. If indeed the two Houſes freely and fully ſitting, had conſented to it, and the people Generally ſubmitted to it, the caſe might ſeem eaſier to reſolve. Butſtill this ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would remain, whether both Senate and people could conſent, without ſin, to the change of Government, lying under ſo many bonds and engagements, to another Power: of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>The Roman State then will not help him: let us ſee our own: <hi>Many perſous</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>have been ſetled in Supreme power, by meer force, without Title of Inheritance, or juſt Conqueſt, and obeyed by the people of this land: and Laws made by forced Parliaments are ſtill in force and obeyed: ſo that the voice of the Nation, with one conſent, ſeems to speak aloud, that thoſe, whoſe Title is held unlawfull, may lawfully be obeyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many anſwers to be given to this: 1. Thoſe times were very dark, in prevailing of Popery, and therefore no preſidents for a Reformed State to imitate. 2. Thoſe people were not perhaps precluded, by ſo many Oaths and Covenants, from alteration of the former Government, as we of this Generation are. 3. The queſtion is not <hi>de facto,</hi> but <hi>de jure,</hi> whether they did will, in ſo doing. The ſcruple is juſtly made, Whether they ought not rather to aſſert (as far as in them lay) the right of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115589:3"/>true Heir; than to cloſe with the uſurper; eſpecially if under our engagements: It they ought in conſcience to aſſert the Right of the true Heir, they ought not to obey (actively) any other, commanding in his prejudice. If they were not bound, by want of power, to aſſert that right, yet the queſtion is, Whether they might either directly, or indirectly, do any act, which might affirm the right of the uſurper, or deny, but ſo much as interpretatively, the juſt Title of the Heir, without being guilty of the ſins of lying, treachery and falſeneſſe; if not of perjury and Vow-breaking: In ſuffering, I confeſſe, if a thief take my purſe, I cannot help it; if I muſt part with that, or my life, I chooſe to loſe my purſe; not for fear leaſt I break the filth or eighth Commandment, but leaſt I break the ſixth, and be guilty of ſelf-murder: yet rather than ſay, he hath autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to take it, I muſt loſe my life. In point of protection, If I be in the hands of theeves, I will deſire ſome of them, to preſerve me from the violence of ſome others: yet muſt I not (to obtain that protection,) ſay, that their robbery is juſt, or good, much leſſe, join with them in robbing others, or be an abetter to their actions, though the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of ſuch abetting, indanger my life. 4. As for our preſent ſubmitting to thoſe Laws, firſt made by uſurpers, and forced Parliaments; we ſay, they have been often ratified (being thought wholſome Laws) by ſucceeding lawfull Parliaments, and ſo make nothing to the caſe in hand: and, perhaps, till then, not to be judged valid Acts.<note place="margin">See that Ordinace of <hi>Aug.</hi> 20 1647. Declaring ſuch Votes paſſed, to be null at the time of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Houſe was the under a force.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hereunto</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>Divines and Caſuiſts give their concurrence,</hi> Azorius, Navarr, Alſted, Paraeus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to theſe we ſay, 1. Its one thing to claim juſtice of a Tyrant (for neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſubſiſtence,) by eſtabliſhed Laws not yet repealed (which perhaps may juſtifie thoſe that are forced to proſecute ſuits under the preſent Courts,) wherein we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the power of the former Laws, which are our birthright, not properly, but by accident, to the power that manages them at preſent. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The reaſon given by the firſt, is this, <hi>The Commonwealth tacitely conſents in this, that though he have no right or Title, yet he may adminiſter Law, to Citizens ſubjected,</hi> facto, <hi>not</hi> jure, <hi>as if he were a Competent Judge, and lawfull Superiour:</hi> But this varies the queſtion two waies; 1. That there is a tacite conſent of all. 2. That he adminiſters the old Laws eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, not any new ones of his own, to the overthrow of the old, which we have ſworn and covenanted to maintain. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The reaſon given by the ſecond, is ſcarcely ſound; <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>they that ſeek the adminiſtration of juſtice, do endeavour to free him from a greater ſin; that he that ſind by uſurping juriſdiction, may not alſo ſin, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitting the adminiſtration of Juſtice.</hi> This perhaps, is but a popiſh nicety; for the queſtion is. Whether in ſo doing, he be not guilty of his former ſin of uſurpation, by complying ſo far with him, as to ſtabliſh his juriſdiction thus uſurped; and whether he ought not rather to ſuffer loſſe, than ſinupon himſelf. 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> But <hi>Paraeus</hi> is of moſt credit, and ſo of moſt weight: <hi>It matters not</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>by what waies or acts</hi> Nimrod, <hi>or</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>or others, got Kingdoms; for the power is one thing which is of God, and the getting, and the uſe of the power is another.</hi> Another more plainly, <hi>when a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is made whom we ſhould obey, it muſt not be looked at, what he is that exerciſeth the power, or by what right or wrong he hath invaded the power,</hi> &amp;c. To this we ſay, firſt, <hi>Paraeus</hi> may be underſtood, to ſpeak of an uſurpation over a free people; engaged by no Oathes or Covenants, to another Government: ſuch I beleeve was <hi>Nimrods</hi> caſe; or if otherwiſe, the queſtion is, Whether a people do not ſin, in ſubmitting to ſuch a power, as in <hi>Ieroboams</hi> caſe; the people revolting from <hi>Rehoboam.</hi> 2. I ſee not how that others words can well be juſtified: is it not to be looked at, whether
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115589:4"/>it be <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> or <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> that exerciſes the power? Is not this (if literally taken) a way, to open a doer, as to inſurrections and ſeditions, if men can but get power to ſuppreſſe the Legall Authority: ſo to diſpenſe with Oaths, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> when ſuch an uſurpation is made? not only, that ſuch may, but muſt be obeyed, heartily, and for conſcience ſake? may we, or muſt we obey every one that hath gotten power, though never ſo wrongfully? might not ſome infer from this ground, Satan, the prince of this world, having uſurped power, over the ſons of diſobedience, muſt be obeyed, as the ordinance of God, foraſmuch as there is no power but of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he gives his own reaſon for it. <hi>And how</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>can it be otherwiſe? for when a perſon, or perſons have gotten ſupreme power, and by the ſame exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all other from authority, either this authority, must be obeyed, or elſe all authority fall to the ground, and ſo confuſion be admitted (worſe than Titular Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe this is a very hard caſe, to naturall reaſon: but perhaps, it is not hard to a Chriſtian; whoſe rule is, Ye muſt not do the leaſt evil, to prevent the greateſt miſery. But is there no remedy, in the whole body of a people, to prevent this? If they would all, in conſcience of their Oaths and Covenants, be conſtant to their duty; either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, or not complying, or ſuffering; what could that power do? whereas if they willingly, and readily comply, with every uſurped power, do they not confirm Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and faſten Tyranny upon themſelves? and by ſuch compliance make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of that uſurpation? If, as is aſſerted, we may lawfully; nay muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, obey ſuch uſurped power in all acts materially good, then is it impoſſible, that any one, whoſe Title is once wronged, can ever be lawfully righted; for it will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſinfull, to help the weaker party, and it cannot, without help, be other then ſuch. And ſuppoſing it lawfull, and our duty, to obey ſuch uſurpers, it will be unlawfull to reſcue our ſelves out of their hands, for it being lawfull to ſubmit, and we bound in conſcience to obey, in what is lawfull, we are bound in conſcience ſo to ſubmit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out endeavouring to get our liberty, or to become the ſtronger party; which without endeavouring it can never be, and ſo we are bound to be perpetuall ſlaves.</p>
            <p>That of the Maſters Mate, throwing the Maſter over-board, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not every way parallell with ours in hand: The neceſſity not alike abſolute: But if the Mate would command the Mariners, by any word, or act, to acknowledge his violence to be juſt, and his Government lawfull, ought they not rather to die then ſin? But when we comply, actively, to the ratifying and ſetling of an uſurped power, with wrong to the right Heir, we ſin; and ſo much the more, if bound by Oathes and Covenants, not to aſſiſt, or comply with any others, neither for fear, nor favour, deſerting our engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (which are the words of the ſolemne Covenant,) <hi>Not ſuffering our ſelves, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or indirectly, by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion or terrour, to be withdrawn from this bleſſed union</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but ſhall all the daies of our lives, zealouſly &amp; conſtantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein againſt all oppoſition, and promote the ſame, according to our power, againſt all lets and impediments whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c. All which, whether it can ſo eaſily be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with, as this Gent. ſeems to hold forth, I leave to every conſcience to conſider.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>ſome speak of a time for ſettlement, they indeed do rather speak for a time of unſettlement,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They mean, if a Government be once ſetled, by the generality of the people, and no power appears to bring it back to the former ſtate, they may better comply with it; <hi>In repub, conſtituta,</hi> not <hi>conſtituenda:</hi> And this is no unſettlement, unleſſe it be an
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115589:4"/>unſetling of an uſurped Government, which men in Covenant, ought to endeavour to their utmoſt power; and however, to be rather paſſive in, than active to the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it; which if it were generally done, might (by the bleſſing of God upon faithfullneſſe to a right Heir, and to our Oaths and Covenants,) perhaps prevail, to make the uſurpers think of ſome better way, of reducing the Government to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient channell: Whereas this way of compliance, faſtens and ſettles them, in their ſin and Government together: And whereas he ſaith, <hi>that may be called a ſettlement, when there is ſuch a way ſetled, that men may have juſtice, if they will; and may enjoy the main end of Magiſtracy, to live a peaceable life, in godlineſſe and honesty.</hi> I anſwer, Such a ſettlement as is pleaded for, is not the way to enjoy the main end of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For how can a people, conſenting readily together, to a violation of ſo ſacred a Covenant, and Oath, ever be like to live a peaceable life, in godlineſſe or honeſty?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And indeed</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>when one is in poſſeſſion by power, and another pretends a Title, what can the body of a Nation do, in this caſe? they cannot judge of Titles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>True, in ſome doubtfull caſes they cannot; but in our caſe, who is ſo ſimple that he cannot judge of the Title, where it is, and where it is not? who hath not, or may not hear, of the Oathes of Allegiance and Supremacy? who hath not heard of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Declarations for the right and Title? Whatever it was in former times, the Title is now clear to every eye; and if it were doubtfull, our engagements are gone out into all the world.</p>
            <p>To that he anſwers: <hi>Surely Oathes are ſacred bonds, and reverend obligements,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet there are faults on both hands: on the one ſide, the ſlighting of an Oath: But we finde ſome part of the Vow and Covenant, to speak of all the daies of our lives</hi> &amp;c. <hi>True it is, the obligation of ſome things may end, as that of the Kings Perſon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To which and the reſt we ſay; the Kings Perſon in <hi>England</hi> never dies, ſaies the Law; ſuch a King we are bound to preſerve. Suppoſe the King had died in wars, or a naturall death, and his Son had been in Arms at his death, would not our Covenant have reached, to binde us to the preſervation of the Sons perſon, as well as of the Fathers? whatever men think now, I am confident, two or three years ago, moſt men would have been of this minde. 2. It is indeed impoſſible, to preſerve that Kings perſon, yet (ſaies the Gent.) <hi>We finde ſome part of the Vow and Covenant, to ſpeak of all the daies of our lives, as to extirpate profaneneſſe, hereſie, blaſphemy, and for Reformation.</hi> All which it were well if the Covenanters would remember to obſerve. But I ſhall remember him of more. <hi>To preſerve the rights and priviledges of Parliament, and the Liberties of the Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. Are theſe things impoſſible now to be preſerved? and if not, do they not ſtill binde us, to endeavour them? 2. His words are worthy to be printed, and printed again, <hi>Will any man that underſtands, and favours Religion and piety, ſay, that the clauſes, which concern Religion and piety, are expired? Did we promiſe to God, in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places and callings, to extirpate profaneneſſe, hereſie, blaſphemy, and to endeavour a Reformed life, in our ſelves and ours, onely till our enemies were overcome, and then to make an end?</hi> (Say the ſame of our promiſes, to preſerve the rights and priviledges of Parliament, and liberties and Laws of the Kingdom,) <hi>What were this, but to ſay unto God, if thou wilt deliver us, we will be bound to thee, till we are delivered, and no longer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Surely this is too like that courſe of carnall</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.14, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But he goes on; <hi>Here it were good to conſider, whether there be any clauſe, in any Oath or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which, in a fair and commonſence, forbids obedience to the commands of the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: much leſſe, when no other can be had, and ſo the Commonwealth muſt go to ruine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We anſwer, yes, there is, by neceſſary conſequence: that clauſe in the Oath or Covenant, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands obedience, and faith, to the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and to the Laws eſtabliſhed, forbids obedience to any other power or Authority, raiſed up againſt them. Nor will that ſalve it which he adds <hi>(when no other can be had)</hi> for another may be had, and might perhaps have been had, ere this, if ſome men in place had not complied with that force put upon the Houſes and Kingdom. If they did it upon antecedent conſent, they are deeply and hainouſly guilty; if upon perſwaſion, or terrour (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their engagements in the Covenant,) yet are they too guilty, to be excuſed, as acceſſaries <hi>poſt factum,</hi> to ſay no more.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115589:5"/>
            <p>But ſaies he, <hi>If the Kings Heirs be not his Succeſſors, how doth that Oath binde? either the word Succeſſors, muſt be ſuperfluous, or elſe it muſt binde to Succeſſors, as well as to Heirs. And it hindes not to a Succeſſor, that is not an Heir, how can it binde to and Heir that is not a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer we ſay, 1. Who keeps the Heir from being a Succeſſor? They that made the Act againſt ſucceſſion; to which this Gent. perhaps gave his Vote; or at leaſt, complies and acts with thoſe, that did ſo Vote; in acting for a Republike in oppoſition to it. 2. The word Succeſſor, is not ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: for it is put, by way of expoſition of the word Heir; who ought to be the Succeſſor. And it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not, how Succeſſor is ſometime taken; In the Oath of Supremacie or Allegiance; it is not meant of any Succeſſor, but a lawfull Succeſſor; as the words expreſſy are. If then, any force debar the ſucceſſion of the right and lawfull Heir, let him conſider, whether they that took that Oath, are not bound to reſiſt that force, if they have any power, and to help to ſettle the Heir: or if they want pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet not to ſubmit willingly to that force, in oppoſition to that right, and in violation of that Oath. Though the Covenant ſpeaks not of the Allegiance to Heirs and Succeſſors, yet the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion refers unto it, <hi>in terminis.</hi> And that (we ſuppoſe,) binds us, to endeavour the ſucceſſion of the Heir: Elſe how could the Lady <hi>Iane</hi> be a Traitor againſt Qu <hi>Mary?</hi> whoſe claim of the Crown, an tecedent to the others enjoyment, could only be a crime, becauſe it prejudiced the Heir, in hindering, as much as in her was, the ſucceſſion. Nor could any thing be Treaſon, which is only derogatory to the ſucceſſion. And if ſuch, as at any time have power, debar a rightfull Heir, they muſt not be puniſhed afterward, when the other is ſtronger, becauſe the ſtrength of the former made it no crime, at the time when it was done. However, the many obligations to Monarchy, as well as to the partia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Monarch, are obligatory though there were a doubt, concerning the perſon. We cannot cloſe with ſuch a party (we think,) but we become acceſſaries, <hi>poſt ſacſum,</hi> to what perhaps it is impoſſible, at preſent, to be helped.</p>
            <p>At laſt he puts a quaerie, <hi>While the Son is in the ſame poſture with the Father, how comes this Oath to plead for diſobedience in regard of the Son; that was aſleep, and ſilent, in regard of the Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The anſwer is, 1. The Son is not altogether in the ſame poſture with the Father: for the Father was in Arms againſt a lawfull, and coordinate Authority of the Kingdom; but the Son, now, is claiming his own right, as Heir to the Crown; hath a good cauſe (ſo far) and a juſt claim; oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, not the ſame power (as ſome think) but unlawfull Martiall uſurpation, over his own perſonall rights, and over the three Eſtates (the ſundamentall Authority of this Kingdom.) the King, Lords and Commons. 2. The Father himſelf was under thoſe pretended crimes (for which he was put to death) then, and before the Covenant was taken, to preſerve his perſon: and the King, the Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> never dies, 3. Diſobedience was not pleaded, to his Authoritative will, but his perſonall will: and ſo the objection was neither ſilent nor aſleep in regard of the Father; but all things being acted is the name of the King and Parliament, his Title was both acknowledged and aſſerted; which is now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, when in regard both of the Son, and of Monarchy it ſelf, it is diſclaimed. 4 If the Son were in any crime, equall with the Father; yet the right or Title to the Crown, upon his Father dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doth quit him from all ſtain, by the Laws of the Land. Therefore obedience may be due to him, and the Oath may ſtand up, to plead for diſobedience to uſurped power, in regard of the Son, which was aſleep, and ſilent, in regard of the father,</p>
            <p>For a concluſion of all: If men were as ſenſible of duty, as they are of danger, and more af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> to ſin, than to ſuffer; I am very confideut, that ſuch weak ſhifts, as large conſciences can finde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> help them ſwallow a Cammell, who heretoſoth ſtrained at a gnat; and ſuch conſulting with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and bloud, would have no place with them: I ſhall only make two requeſts; One, that the Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of the Tract, would conſider ſeriouſly, whether the maintaining, and abetting thoſe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with the fiſt of wickedneſſe, be the way to peace? The Other, That the Lord would guide all L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of truth and peace, into the way of peace (which is Righteouſneſſe,) and that be would grant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the people of the Land, faithfullneſſe to their Oathes and Covenants, and ſincerity and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, that they may have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EPHESIANS 5.11.</bibl>
                  <p>Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 TIMOTHY 5.22.</bibl>
                  <p>Neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
